[Music]
hello everyone it is active live live
stream number 45.0
it's may 27 2022 and we're discussing
the paper the free energy principle made
simpler but not too simple
welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on this slide
this is a recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
if you want to learn more about the live
streams or any of the other projects to
get involved at activelab head over to
activeinference.org
we're in stream number 45.0
our goal is to learn and discuss this
very interesting paper the free energy
principle made simpler but not too
simple by carl firsten lancelot de costa
north sajid connor heinz
kai ulitoffer
gregorius pavliotis and thomas parr
and just like with all the dot zero
videos and indeed all the videos this is
an introduction and an overview to a
quite technical and
lengthy ish paper it's not a review or a
final word this is like the opening
context for some of the coming
discussions we're going to have in the
following weeks and beyond
and we're going to
first just say hello introduce the big
question the ames claims abstract and
roadmap
then we're going to give an overview of
some of the keywords that are in the
paper
then we're going to go through the
sections of the paper with a focus on
some of the key points the formalisms
and the figures especially
so it should be a great discussion
and
let's get into it we'll start with just
an introduction and saying hello so i'm
daniel i'm a researcher in california
and el paso brock brock thanks for
joining and for all the contributions in
this dot zero
yeah so exciting to be here and
participate in the academic lab and
um
yeah just really drawn to this topic and
this paper is a great starting point for
that it's really
got a lot of um
you know detail
uh that uh to dig into and
a lot to learn so
yeah
okay
so
one of the big questions or one way to
state the big question
was
what are
the foundations of the free energy
principle
and what does it contribute
in the paper they write that they start
from a description of the world in terms
of a random dynamical system systems
changing through time
and end up with a description of
self-organization as sentient sensing
active behavior and that's active
inference so
that's the question that we're wondering
about we're all wondering about what is
the basis
and the essence and the implications of
the free energy principle
what would you say about that or what
were some big questions that you had
coming into and out of this paper
my biggest question around like the free
energy principle is kind of it's it's
general how general is it where is it
and then
because it seems so
they say in the paper also it's like
it's pretty simple so kind of
tautological in some sense um
uh
so
yeah that's
one of my questions
you know where does it begin where does
it end and um
like how general is it the other
question is um
[Music]
yeah how
how does it uh
emerge or um
what does it look like at different
scales
awesome so we'll be returning to
questions again and again
let's check out the aims and the claims
of the paper
so again it's the free energy principle
made simpler but not too simple
and the authors are listed here
the
paper describes that it's trying to
present the free energy principle as
simply as possible but without
sacrificing too much technical detail
and that's sort of a pun slash
self-reference being that's what
modeling in that pareto optimal or bayes
optimal way is and that's gonna come
back as a theme again and again giving
information but not over fitting nor
underfitting
and then several claims that they make
are that they're going to step through
the formal arguments
that lead from the description of a
world as a random dynamical system
to the description of self-organization
in terms of active inference and
self-evidencing
they're going to discuss bayesian
mechanics
and
how those bayesian mechanics have the
same starting point as quantum
statistical and classical mechanics
and then they're going to differentiate
this bayesian mechanics for particular
systems from some of these previously
mentioned mechanics
in that
careful attention is paid to the way
that the internal states of something
couple to its external states
some of the aims and claims although
many more will be
introduced and are discussed in the
paper
any thoughts on that
or if you'd like to oh yeah god
yeah um
just um
well i mean that uh
essentially that it's you know it's just
self-evidencing
self-describing system
um
again just very it seems
to fit with a lot of uh
different domains and a lot of like just
observed experience
so
cool would you like to
read the abstract
sure
this paper provides a concise
description of the free energy principle
starting from a formulation of random
dynamical systems in terms of a
legovin equation and ending with a
bayesian mechanics that can be
read as a physics
of sentience
it rehearses the key
steps using standard results from
statistical physics
these steps entail
by establishing a particular partition
of states based on
conditional independencies inherent from
sparsely coupled dynamics to unpacking
the implications of
this partition
in terms of bayesian inference and three
describing the paths of particular
states with
a variational principle of least action
teleologically the free energy principle
offers a normative account of
self-organization in terms of optimal
bayesian design and decision making
in the sense of maximizing marginal
likelihood or
bayesian model evidence
in summary starting from a description
of the world in terms of random
dynamical systems we end up with a
description of self-organization
essential behavior that can be
interpreted as self-evidencing namely
self-assembly out of places or
active inference
awesome okay
let's go to the road map
so this paper has
layout and it'll be awesome to hear from
the authors about why they've laid it
out as well as numerous other details so
we're looking forward to those
discussions
in section one
is an introduction
and they wrote
at the end of the introduction the
remaining sections describe the free
energy principle each section that's two
through eight
focuses on an equation or sections
the ensuing narrative is meant to be
concise
taking us from the beginning to the end
as succinctly as possible
to avoid disrupting the narrative we use
footnotes to address questions that are
commonly asked at each step
we also use figure legends captions to
supplement the narrative with examples
from neurobiology
so there's a main narrative thread
that's going to touch on sections two
through eight each of these being like a
single or a cluster of formalisms
and then especially in the footnotes
which are formulated as questions and in
the figure captions which are
sometimes quite lengthy and include
examples and citations and so on
more of the biological details and
inspiration are added but the main line
narrative
is going to be touching on these
formal areas
systems states and fluctuates steady
states and non-equilibrium three
particles partitions and things in four
self-organization to self-evidencing in
five
lagrangian generalized states in
bayesian filtering and six
statistical to classical particles in
seven
path integrals planning and curious
particles in eight and section nine will
be a conclusion
so we're going to
next discuss the keywords
at an overview level and just describe
like some of the
broader topics that might lead someone
to find this paper be curious about it
or want to cite it in one of those
domains
and then we're going to just jump right
into the introduction each of the nine
sections will be clearly indicated which
section we're in and we'll be following
the order of the paper
bringing in a few other resources as
we saw fit in the preparation
and we're just gonna
focus on
some of the dots
connecting a few and leaving many many
for the dot one and the dot two
discussions
because it's again a paper with a lot of
formalisms
and a lot of rich
topics so we're just going to give this
overview
and try to
front load the contextualization
and then continue to unpack and develop
this and work on our shared
understanding in the coming weeks
the keywords that were listed were
bayesian
non-equilibrium
self-organization
variational inference
and markov blanket
so
brock
tell us about bayesian
bayesian analysis um
so it's
basically a
um
yeah it's an analysis method for
determining the
posterior probability which is
um
basically your
in inactive inference and
it's
going to be something like
your beliefs
after
having evidence added to
your prior beliefs which
are
something approximately like a
hypothesis
um
so i have the equation here
and
also the word explanation that's
essentially what i just said um
so you're adding you know observation to
hypothesis and changing um
trying to reduce
the um
trying to approximate the
uh
this phv here uh over e the processor
probability so
um
is
pretty foundational too
yeah a lot of statistics and physics and
other things
um
thank you yes totally agreed bayesian
statistics it's a big topic
and just like you said it's about how
prior beliefs meet incoming evidence and
how that is updated to form posterior
you know after the evidence beliefs
versus before the evidence and that can
be done in this continuous cycle
and a lot of the variables that we're
going to be seeing and talking about
have
interpretations of being one of these
for example it might be a variable that
represents a system's prior about
something or something might come in and
that might be
evidence so
we're going to be working within a
bayesian statistical framework
rather than for example a frequentist
p-value-driven statistical framework but
we'll come to these details along the
way
how about non-equilibrium
this is um
i think a
much fuzzier
topic um
like the tradition like historically
you know science studied like
equilibrium state systems and
non-equilibrium state systems are like
more uh
relatively newer things
um and so
non-equilibrium is is um
these are things that were mentioned in
the papers like flows uh between
transitions of uh between like finite
sets of states having an attractor in a
system that over time
the you know
perturbations in the system um still
act as a set of characteristic states to
which the system is attracted over time
um
so
and non-equilibrium being like a higher
energy level state that is you know to
its local environment
um
but nonetheless
distinct definite separate
and overtime
continuous
so just looking at the animation you put
here it's like the brick
at some time scale
is out of equilibrium like the brick
will also dissolve but for some
model of a certain time frame hours it
could be seen as being spatially or just
materially in an equilibrium and then
looking at these two moving entities
it's kind of like two kinds of
non-equilibrium there's like the low bar
non-equilibrium this mechanical bird on
the right side the water dipper and so
it is returning to these characteristics
states
it's not just staying in one location
it's returning to drink the water again
and again so it's not in spatial
equilibrium
but also there's like this stationarity
or there's something about it that is
constrained
and then the um ostensibly living bird
i guess
the on the cartoon on the left
is like
non-equilibrium of an even
higher or more complex type because that
bird might like fly away or do something
else so there's like a gradient from
things that are like the ball at the
bottom of the bowl
in equilibrium
and then progressively mechanical
systems that are returning to attracting
states and then what does it mean for
biological systems to be or to be
modeled as returning to attracting
states like sleep or
a certain body temperature certain blood
glucose
any other thoughts on that or we can
carry on
yeah just yeah this is a different like
time scale set of states larger
smaller
and
uh
navigating traversing those states yeah
internally right and so
i guess it just it depends where you're
drawing the
the time scale
awesome but they can be modeled
differently like that right
how about
self-organization
i think this one like
um
maybe it sounds
uh just this complex but i think this is
like really familiar
for most people they have a good idea of
what this is
um
[Music]
and like yeah these like examples here
um
of uh non-equilibrium
systems um
that you know have some
um
symmetry asymmetry of constraints that
over time causes them to
take a particular path through that
um
set of states towards one attractor
or another
um
cellular meiosis and mitosis here um
black hole mergers
nuclear fission nuclear fusion
very large very small
meso in between scales here um
in the paper um
[Music]
referencing fep they were they said it
was fep was about kind of turning
on its head this traditional what what
must things do in order to exist
framing
of
systems and physics to
if if it exists
what must they do
and so
this is saying
you know we have now a bayesian
evidence of
black hole mergers
what must it be doing for that data
now that new evidence to
um
yeah exist like
what how
will
how does nuclear fusion you know how
does that turn into two atoms turning
into one atom what must it be do it
instead of
the other way around
awesome yeah big
topic many angles on it but sometimes
those inversions
like actual constants paper that we
discussed in live stream 34 with um
it's about how you got there
so
conditioned on some thing which we're
going to return to existing being
perceived being modeled
what must that thing be doing in order
to exist
not what has to happen for the thing to
exist but we're going to come back to
that
and then um the last two will just give
a first
coat of paint because we're gonna see
them in their technical glory soon so
what is variational inference about
um i'm actually less
clear on this but
uh
related to bayesian inference it's about
approximating that um
posterior probability the
um after
um
things happen like but what
you know um
to what resolution can you kind of you
know what precision can you
state about that and also trying to have
a lower bound
for the marginal likelihood of evidence
of the observed data so how likely are
you to see
um
the data that would cause that to be
that would lead to the processor
probability being what it is
that was my understanding
of this
yeah awesome
what is the divergence um it'll be
awesome to hear the authors and others
perspectives but
places where we've seen variational
bayesian inference before first off it's
not an innovation of active inference
variational autoencoders and variational
bayesian methods are being used in
active inference
with
the partial novelty of action being
considered as a parameter rather than
just sensory parameters
but it's used in situations where exact
base
is intractable
and sampling based approaches like monte
carlo
are also
not tractable or not plausible and so
variational inference is about
minimizing the divergence between
q and p
mind your q's and p's as they say up
there
and
making sure that q is from a family of
distributions that is tractable and easy
to optimize even if p
is something that is challenging
instead a different distribution for
example one that has a shape looking
more like a parabola more like a bowl
can be fit with q
and then there's still some detail like
if p truly were bimodal
would you want the one that identifies
and rests q on top of one hump and
ignores the other hump
or would you want the cue that is kind
of centered at a place where neither of
the p humps are
but contains some density in both so
those are some detailed questions but in
general it's about minimizing the
divergence between q and p
as a means of approximating
what
exact base would be doing in the
asymptote if the divergence were zero
you would be
having the perfect approximation of q on
p
and then anywhere other than the
divergence being zero
there's a monotonic way for you to get
towards that
and then
markov blanket which we're gonna come to
in multiple formalisms but just
what
comes to mind when you hear markov
blanket and what did you want to show
here
everything this one is like i feel like
this is the most
easy to understand one somehow it's um
like this picture here
you can see is a bunch of dots that are
different colors right and you have um
like a circular concentric circles here
um
and that's you know to at this large
inside the large square scale
there's this like yellow
line that separates
all the outside dark blue from the
inside orange and red
and
but there's also an an orange inside
circle
and these these yellow and orange
are kind of in a
um
in a relationship that
keeps the dark blue and the red separate
independent of each other
but you also have
these obviously these
smaller scale inside the red inside the
yellow inside the orange here
right these other scale of the same
thing like that it is
um
in some sense either
recursive or fractal or
um you know locally
having this same kind of dynamic of two
layers
um conditioned on each other to keep
an external
um
and an internal state independent of
each other
um
awesome yes which is everything i feel
like
it's every
thing
which we're going to be getting to
mind the space
and um
[Music]
it's an exciting topic and there's a lot
of ongoing discussions and developments
here's a recent paper by casper hesp and
there's many other valuable commentaries
on emperor's new markov blankets by
yella brundenberg
which was previously on a live stream so
there's many many technical and
philosophical and implementation
discussions around identifying markov
blankets reifying them
and so on
and we're gonna get there so
into the paper we go
we're in section one
introduction
they write
um it is said
that the free energy principle is
difficult to understand no citation
who's saying that no one is saying that
this is ironic on three counts first the
fep is so simple that it is almost
taught logical
circular reasoning
indeed philosophical accounts compare
its explanandam
what it explains to a desert landscape
in the sense of quine aquinian desert
landscape
as per what clark wrote and we'll return
to that in a second
a second reason for the irony
is
a tenant of the fep is that everything
must provide an accurate account of
things that is as simple as possible
including itself
finally the fep rests on straightforward
results from statistical physics so one
is
it's not difficult to understand it's so
simple it's circular
two is how can it be difficult to
understand
when everything is as simple as it must
be including the fep literature
that's that's some high level irony and
then the third reason is
how could it be difficult to understand
when it rests on straightforward results
from statistical physics and then i just
wanted to highlight this clark 2013
citation and the desert landscape
because that seems like kind of like an
oblique reference
but here's what clark and also here's
two representations of desert landscapes
so they're not all bad in fact but what
clark wrote was
referring to radicalisms that might
exist within this framework
in extending the models to include
action
action-oriented predictive processing
which is very very similar to active
inference
we might simultaneously do away with the
need to appeal to goals and rewards
replacing them with a more austere
construct of predictions
so i don't want
to do this or i'm not rewarded by doing
that i'm just making predictions and
expectations about what might happen and
then fulfilling them or diverging from
those fulfillments
and so um
that is this desert landscape vision
there are neither goals nor reward
signals as such
instead there are only learnt and
species specific so kind of
developmental and evolutionary
expectations across spatial and temporal
scales that are in control of perception
action loops
and so
what are we explaining or explaining
away that's this desert landscape notion
and that's how the authors are beginning
the paper with a sort of preemptive
tripartite broadside
dissuading one from thinking that this
is going to be difficult to understand
before launching into the subsequent
eight sections that might give you some
um
evidence to the contrary but yeah any
thoughts on that
i just thought yeah the desert liquidium
desert landscape very apt description
and um
yeah physical
sort of yep
it lines up and
yeah like i said that this uh
it does seem tautological like a lot of
these concepts if you think about them
from like the statistical physics it's
like
obviously but um
then there's just a lot of
area there to be covered right
so yes and also note that clark in 2013
wrote i remain unconvinced even if the
austere description is possible this
would not justify the claim that this is
the better tool for understanding the
cognitive economy so
it's it is intractable so it's like yeah
what yeah
yep awesome
so
still in the introduction
the author is right before starting it
might help to clarify what the free
energy principle is and why it is big
question alert
many theories in the biological sciences
are answers to the question what must
things do in order to exist
and some answers but we could think of
probably many others that people have
raised so if if you ask somebody what
does something have to do in order to
exist some answers could be like well it
has to resist dissipation it has to
replicate or it has to reproduce or
propagate some way like there's stuff it
has to do
to be there
the fep turns this question on its head
and asks
if things exist what must they do
more formally if we can define what it
means to be something
can we identify the physics or dynamics
that that thing must possess
to answer this question the fep calls on
some mathematical truisms that follow
from each other
then they write
much like hamilton's principle of least
action the fep is not a falsifiable
theory about the way things behave
it is a description
of things that are defined in a
particular way
and for
more reading on this here's a 2018
interview with fortier and myself and
with carl firsten
and here there's some discussion
around
notions of false of ability can the fep
be falsified or what is the relevance of
falsification
which is a frequentist idea
in this bayesian metabasian post
bayesian whatever
epoch or mode that we're in and just one
really interesting quote is um
from carl i would assert that the notion
that a framework can have the attribute
falsifiable is a category error
the notion of falsifibility is thus a
very weak notion
because it's actually reflecting
rejecting a null hypothesis in favor of
an alternative hypothesis
that has some limitations
um
including the sort of
uh the transcendental argument on
falsification which is just that
belief is rarely scrutinized using a
falsificationist framework
and then dropping from the
transcendental argument into a more
history of statistics and science
when we move from frequentism towards
bayesian statistics
where the p-value and so on and the
parametric distributions are seen as
like special cases but not the whole
substance of the statistics
carl's suggesting that a better way to
frame evidence-based selection of
hypotheses
which is ostensibly what falsification
is after as well
is in terms of how much empirical
evidence is accrued by competing
hypotheses and that's quite a different
model than uh can and then falsify the
ones that aren't true let's shoot down
the ones that don't exist so this is
quite an interesting area
um
what would you say or add to this
there's a word uh varus militude
i think that is
exactly what he's um describing here
again
just
how much evidence is accrued rather than
yeah i mean
that's in practice how it works
so i don't completely understand the
notion of phosphate valuability is it's
really important
but
um like like derock um had this notion
of beauty or
and he's saying look if the equation is
really beautiful
then
maybe you check your experiment first
um
so
like you were saying it's kind of like
um that's not falsifiable but
then what do you mean by not falsifiable
and that is that you're not examining
that claim it's kind of there's a
you know infinite regression there of
falsifiability
that makes it intractable which is why
taking the opposite approach of just
stacking up the evidence
is
you know a way to make the sa it's the
same thing
you know but a tractable version kind of
of it right so
awesome
they're right
again picking up on that last quotation
there that the fep is not a falsifiable
theory about the way things behave
it's a description of things that are
defined in a particular way
let's talk about utility is such a
description
if the fep is indeed a description is it
useful
in itself the answer is probably no oh
well then we can stop reading
in the sense that the principle of least
action does not tell you how to throw a
ball
however the principle of least action
furnishes everything we need to know to
simulate the trajectory of a ball in a
particular
instance
in the same sense
the fep allows one to simulate and
predict the sentient behavior of a
particle person artifact or agent i.e
some
thing
this allows one to build sentient
artifacts or use simulations as
observation models of particles or of
those other mentioned types of systems
these simulations rest upon specifying a
generative model
that is apt to describe the behavior of
the particle or person at hand
at this point
committing to a specific generative
model can be taken as a commitment to a
specific and falsifiable theory
later we will see examples of these
simulations
so it's like
the linear regression concept
is not even where you would want to
focus the brunt of your falsifying
effort
but
if there are
two different linear aggression models
we might ask which one is preferable or
which one is falsified by doing some
subsequent perturbation or experiments
but the linear regression framework
is like a framework hence not
falsifiable in the way that people often
expect
and deploying a specific generative
model
analogous to like a specific linear
aggression model but different
that is where there's a commitment to a
falsifiable theory well i think the
amygdala connects to this that way
that could be tested and that evidence
could be evaluated within a
falsification or bayesian base factor
framework
falsifying the concept of generative
models
they would be have crossed that bridge
and now could be engaging in
falsification and evidence comparison
within
some constrained space
anything to add on that as we close the
introduction
yeah just again wait this is a linear
model versus a general model like
the linear model will yield some
approximation that's not a necessarily a
real
um
[Music]
possible observation to falsify
the generative model
will produce many
things that you might not observe
possibly but um some that you will and
then could potentially be falsified
like it gives specific examples so
yes it's almost like it takes this this
miso scale
and it it
separates the the milk from the cream
and the fep
flies over falsification
and then once you're committed to a
specific generative model it's actually
written down not just speculated that it
could be written down then it's like oh
well then it's trivial or against it so
it kind of separated out the framework
like language as a framework like dave
just mentioned in the chat how would you
falsify a language you would not any
more than you would falsify a conceptual
framework so
one could not falsify
a language like english
but things that are said within english
might be amenable to being tested once
they're actually said using that
framework
very interesting evidence stacked up or
not versus alternatives
just like
language or
evolution awesome
so recall the roadmap
we're now going to head into the next
sections each of which is going to be
building on each other in this concise
narrative
however also
semi stand alone
in their focus
and we're just going to do basically a
first pass and some contextualization
because we have a lot of time in the
coming weeks to discuss these topics in
more detail
so we're going to go to section two
systems
states and fluctuations
okay
so they write
we start by describing the world with
the stochastic differential equation
pavliotis 2014.
so this is um a citation to the book
stochastic processes and applications of
diffusions processes
um
and
uh
just one preliminary note this is not
the same sentence as the world is a
stochastic differential equation
we start by describing
the world with a stochastic differential
equation so
leave your realism at the door we're
describing models here
they write why start here
the principal reason is that we want a
description that is consistent with
physics
here's some discussion questions what
does it mean to be consistent with
physics
what does it mean to be consistent with
physics in theory or in principle or in
practice
and then they write
this follows because things like the
schrodinger equation in quantum
mechanics
area a
fluctuation theorems in statistical
mechanics
area b
and lagrangian formulation of classical
mechanics
area c
three different mechanics
quantum statistical and classical
can all be derived from this starting
point
so we're going back to like the last
common ancestor of those three different
mechanics
and then that is where bayesian
mechanics is going to also be initiated
from
in short if one wants a physics of
sentience this is the place to start
why start where
where are we going
why are we going
anything you want to add here
um
no i think again just that yeah that
that's all these scare physics it's it's
odd that you would
be able to reproduce
you know derive all these things from
something
that's not
fundamental or
important in some way
so
awesome
they write
we are interested in systems that have
characteristic states this means the
system has a pullback attractor
the sets of states that the system will
come to occupy from any initial state so
the rubber band is going to pull back to
its resting
state if it's allowed to
and formalism
that stochastic differential equation
describing the rate of change of the
states so x are the states the tau is
the time and the dot notation is the
derivative with respect to time
so how states are changing
is
equal to
their flow f of x f for flow
and
random fluctuations omega
so like a signal and a noise term
there's the the flow the ocean current
and then there's the vibration that
isn't the directed flow
and this
separation
of scales is going to come back again
and again
so
dot notation again means the derivative
with respect to time so how things are
changing with respect to time
through time
this
yellow
means that time and causality are baked
into everything that follows in the
sense that states cause their motion
this equation is itself an approximation
to a simpler mapping from some variables
to changes in those variables with time
this follows from a separation into
states and random fluctuations implicit
in formalism one where states change
slowly in relation to fast fluctuations
so if
this term the noise term is dominant
then
there will not be movements
flow like movement on a manifold
um
[Music]
there's some more details but
things are changing in different ways
different kind of stochastic equations
that are going to be presented here and
in the book in the citations
they help us see different parts of how
we can use dynamical models
to understand
physics and specifically the physics of
particular cognitive sentient systems
then in the footnote they ask a question
why is the flow not a function of time
and that's what we're going to return to
in dot one
how is time dealt with
or not dealt with similarly or
differently than other frameworks or
other physics
and then just to stay on this formalism
one and then
please give any other thoughts
this last line of one p of x equals
question mark
the next step
shared by all physics so those three
areas that we described
classical statistical quantum and
bayesian
is to ask whether anything can be said
about the probability density over the
states the question mark in one
so this is the common grounding
this is the last common ancestor of the
multiple physics
and now we're going to take it in a
different direction
a lot can be said about this probability
density p of x
which can be expressed in two
complementary ways
and this is going to introduce
a
very important distinction and dialectic
here are the two complementary ways
left side blue
density dynamics using the focker planck
equation
aka also known as the forward klomogorov
here's formalism too
the focker planck equation describes the
change in density due to random
fluctuations and the flow of states
through state space
this is like a field
model and then the second complementary
way in orange on the right side
in terms of the probability of a path
through state space using the path
integral formulation and they write for
formalism three
conversely the path integral formulation
considers the probability of a
trajectory
or path in terms of its action
so
what are two things that you can say or
more about the probability density
what are two complementary ways that it
can be expressed
what are important similarities and
differences
between this focker planck formalism two
approach
and
the
path integral formulation of formalism
three
are there other
complementary ways to say it or other
ways to say what is here but this is
just to introduce what's going to be
very important and going to be moved
back and forth in the course of this
paper which is one representation that's
more field-like continuum-like
and then another representation that's
going to be more trajectory and
path-based
what do you see in there
um yeah we
we discussed this like really briefly
about
um
[Music]
you know like a continuous
space versus a kind of discrete or
instantaneous space like
there's some
um
mostly i guess metaphor there analogy um
but when you just ask this question of
what are you know other ways to say this
like it's it's um
the action trajectory their uh path is
like a
sounds like like a like an action
density or an energy density like where
the where is the kind of um
you know path of of the energy and the
whole system gonna um
you know invents itself right so it's
it's like an action density gradient or
something like this right
um
yeah
cool
real interesting
both the are plank and the path
integral formulations
the the formalism 2 3 dialectic
inherit their functional form from
assumptions about the statistics of
random fluctuations in one
so recall one
with the flow and the random fluctuation
term
for example the most likely path or path
of least action
is the path taken when the fluctuations
take their most likely value of zero
so
we're gonna
explore this more but the path of least
action is not using action in the same
way that active states are
exactly
path of least action does not mean the
laziest or the least energetically
costly or the least mobile thing to do
it's not that it is so that is
what we're going to explore
what does it mean
to minimize action
in this framework
the motion on the path of least action
is just the flow without random
fluctuations
so if the question were you're trying to
run in a straight line forward
there's two forces there's the flow of
you running forward and then there's
your thermal vibrations
so
in one limit
the flow might absolutely be
overwhelming the random fluctuation of
least action would be that person
running forward
conversely if that person was like the
size of one
molecule they would be being buffeted by
stochastic
thermal vibration
and so they would not be following that
path of least action the same way
this metaphor hopefully doesn't
misrepresent
but paths of least action will figure
prominently in the following sections of
the paper
especially when considering systems that
behave in a precise or predictable way
we will denote the most likely states
and paths with a bold typeface so it can
be a little subtle sometimes and so
we'll try to um clarify notation and get
assistance as we can but like this is
like a bold x like a bold x through t
is the minimization of that unbolded
function
with respect to the action a
of those states through time
and that is going to be related to the
change
in x through time being just only the
flow
so here it was like x dot of t
equals the flow of x plus a noise term
here if the noise term is zero
you can drop it
and then they write
although equivalent
the falk are plank and the path integral
formalisms
this dialectic that we've discussed the
formalisms provide complementary
perspectives on dynamics
did we mention that they're different
but complementary
the former deals with time dependent
probability densities over states
the latter
path integral considers time independent
densities over paths
the density overstates at a particular
time is the time marginal of the density
over trajectories
these probabilities bayesian
probabilities bayesian statistics
can be conveniently quantified in terms
of their negative logarithms or
potentials
leading to surprisal and action
respectively
so
we'll
explore the formalisms more but just to
note that the fancy i the fracture i
is the joint distribution
and it is going to be
a negative log
on the joint distribution p
and then similarly a the action
is going to be on those same variables
in a slightly different way
being
looking like a surprise
conditioned upon x sub 0 the starting
conditions
and we're going to go into more
detail in the coming weeks
any more comments on section two or
we'll continue to three
no i yeah that's
awesome
section three solutions steady states
and non-equilibrium
so far so sections one and two
we have equations that describe the
relationship between the dynamics of a
system
and probability densities over
fluctuations states and their paths
this is sufficient to elaborate most
physics
big if true
here's where the
for example
we could use the fock or plank or the
path integral formalism so either side
of that dialectic
to derive quantum mechanics where the
focker planck becomes the schrodinger
wave equation
mechanics one quantum
we could focus on systems that comprise
statistical ensembles of similar states
to derive stochastic and statistical
mechanics in terms of fluctuation
theorems statistical mechanics mechanics
number two
finally we could consider large systems
in which the fluctuations are averaged
away
to derive classical mechanics
such as electromagnetism
and
dot general relativity classical
mechanics
mechanics number three
all of these mechanics quantum
statistical
classical acquire boundary conditions
to give the examples
the schrodinger potential in quantum
mechanics
the heat bath or reservoir in
statistical mechanics and the classical
potential for lagrangian
classical mechanics
at this point the fvp steps back
i wonder what space it's in
and asks
where do these boundary conditions come
from
indeed this was implicit in
schrodinger's question in the famous
article what is life 1944
where schroedinger wrote how can the
events in space and time
which take place within the spatial
boundary of a living organism
be accounted for by physics and
chemistry
and this is a bit of a um
nod slash reference to the paper of
ramstead at all in 2018
answering schrodinger's question of free
energy formulization formulation so this
was a really
impactful and relevant paper that
started
a discussion around the fep and
multi-scale fep and self-organizing
complex biological systems and so on
so
anything
to add about these mechanics and their
similarities and differences
markup blankets
i'll just leave it there
they're everywhere
uh in formalism six
we're going to go into it hopefully in
the discussions but just um in live
stream number 32 on stochastic chaos and
markov blankets
just to show where these similar
equations were
represented
we talked about how the helmholtz
decomposition
could be used
to take a field
and decompose it into
multiple sections
there's the divergence term
which is like um or the gradient term
which is like you're on some landscape
and the ruler that's the most angled
just going straight up the hill that's
like the divergence term and that might
be useful for going up or down a hill as
fast as possible then there's this
solenoidal or curl
flow term
and that is like an iso contour
and those two are part of the classical
helmholtz decomposition
and then there's this capital lambda
which is the housekeeping term as it was
referred to in 32
and we explored it a bit but it reflects
the way that that landscape is also
influenced by movement so we wondered if
that was like kind of like walking
around on a trampoline where you can't
just snapshot the um topographical map
and then do your navigation on the fixed
map but there's some change there
we'll come back to that later
so that's section three on solutions
steady states and non-equilibria
now we're going to really get to mark
off blankets
particles partitions and things
in section 4.
all right so
what do you see in figure one
yeah i mean see
uh these two
inner
red and green conditioned on each other
that
um
keep these
external and internal states on the
outside
separate
they still have
conditional
relationship between
like the sensory states the external
states and the active states the
internal states but
not directly with each other right
so
awesome um so they wrote in the caption
it's an influence diagram
i believe it's also fairly to say it's a
bayes graph but we're thinking of the
arrows as influence and the nodes like
the circles as variables
it's a particular partition of states
particular is a pun because it's it's
one specific partitioning it's not the
only partitioning but it's a particular
one that we're sharing with you
and it's partitioning that
into a particle
into something that's like
distinguishing figure from ground
and the four
states that get partitioned
are internal states and external states
that are separated by a markov blanket
comprised of the sensory and active
states
there's a lot that could be said and
we're going to continue to explore but
just to give a few more notes
the partitioning entails that all of
these states come into existence in a
model specific way at the same time so
it's not like there's some feature of
the world that just is fundamentally an
internal state
it's the relationship between
an internal and external state
conditioned on a blanket by which all of
those assignments can be made
it's like an incomplete sentence
to have one referenced without the other
also we have the um names of the states
mu for internal and ita for external
and it's kind of like they almost look
like flips of each other
then s for sensory states incoming info
a for action active states outgoing
actions
so we have eta external s sensory a
active and mu internal states
and then
there's a few
couples of states sets of states that we
are going to care about and the
equations that describe them have super
different implications so one set of
states that's interesting to compare
together is the blanket states b
is the set of s and a
and that's more aligned with the pearl
1988 formulation of the markov blanket
or boundary where it was an undirected
blanket
and
fristen and others have developed this
notion of like a two-way
partitioning so the blanket is the set
of both s and a
the particular states
pi
not to be confused with pi
the policy selection in the po mdp
the particular states are b
and mu
so the blanket and mu so the particular
states are internal active and sensory
everything except for external so the
particle is like the cell
the boundary and the internal generative
model
and then there's the autonomous states
alpha
which is just a and mu
and one way to think about those states
are like
if you were to design the system
those are the states that you can
control
you can't directly control the sensory
input
which is the only thing that
differentiates the autonomous from the
particular states
you can't directly control what photons
hit the retina but you could control
your interpretation
and your action for where your eyes move
which might absolutely influence which
photons do hit the retina but the
autonomous states are the ones that
there's a degree of agency over
in a way that is slightly different from
just the
consideration of the blankets and the
internal states
let's continue to talk about some of the
formalism
the conditional independencies
which are going to be uh
let's pull back one more
in associating some of these
equations of motion
with a unique non-equilibrium steady
state or nest density
we have a somewhat special setup in
which the influences entailed by the
equations of motions place constraints
on the conditional independences
of the nest density
these conditional independencies can be
used to identify a particular partition
of states
into external sensory active and
internal states as shown in the figure
this is an important move
in what space
because it separates the states of a
particle
internal states and their sensory and
active states the particular states
from the remaining i.e external states
to do this we have to establish how the
causal dynamics in one underwrite
conditional independencies
this can be done simply by using the
curvature or second derivative of
surprisal as follows so how is the
second derivative of surprise related to
causal
sparse dynamics
in your own words what is the formal
description of a marco blanket
what's this sort of minimal
markov blanket this is a slide from
livestream 26 on bayesian mechanics this
is like an undirected blanket we don't
have s and a separated just b
intermediating and partitioning
making mu and etsa conditionally
independent
and what about the fristen blankets type
with sense and action separated what
about nested markov blankets and so on
and so on but just to look at seven we
basically have
x u and v
x sub u and x sub v
are conditionally
independent conditioned upon
b
the blanket
dot dot fancy i surprise
d squared of surprise
partial derivative second derivative of
surprise
dot equals zero
what does it mean how is the second
derivative of surprise related to causal
dynamics and the
partitioning but continuing with a
sparse coupling notion
sparse coupling means that any two
states are conditionally independent if
one state does not influence the other
tautology number
five
this is an important observation namely
that sparse coupling implies the
non-equilibrium steady state density
with conditional independencies
in turn
this means any dynamical influence graph
with absent or directed edges admits a
markov blanket
so if your variables are all connected
to each other it's a fully connected
social network it's a fully connected
statistical model
then
i guess you could argue it has a blanket
with respect to some other things that
you didn't model or you could get into
that whole question but within that
model there are no blanket partitions to
make
if there are any absent edges
then
there are some states
which upon knowing them make some other
states conditionally independent
they give some more technical details
and then they raise a question in the
footnote why does the particular
partition comprise four sets of states
we'll talk about that in
dot one
continuing on sparse coupling and
formalism nine we can define sparse
coupling as the solution to this
equation in which all the terms are
identically zero
so
what terms are zero
what is the reading of this equation
meaning under what situations are they
zero are they being measured and
said to be estimated at zero are they
being dictated to be zero so what terms
are zero what does that mean in nine
sparse coupling means the jacobian
coupling states u and v is zero so on
either side of the blanket is zero
look in seven
u and v they're on the they're on either
side of the blanket conditioned upon
that blanket existing
i.e there's an absence of direct
coupling from one of those to the other
this definition precludes
solenoidal coupling with u that depends
on v
because h and gamma
are positive definite sparse coupling
requires associated elements of the
solenoidal operator and the hessian to
vanish at every point in state space
which in turn implies conditional
independence
so
what is being shown here
but just to give one more visual way of
looking at it this was figure eight from
live stream 32
and
um we had
basically uh
six
variables
that were in two clusters of three
and they were like two communicating
entities
and so they were being coupled by this
like one to four connection
and so up here on the top left there's
strong coupling within nodes one two and
three
and then there's strong coupling within
this click of four five and six
and then there was a sparse coupling
between the systems with a 1 4
and there is also somewhat of a sparse
coupling within
the click because they're not all black
squares
so
we'll return to this and it's again on
the theme of how is sparse coupling
related to the particular partition
and a bayesian mechanics for particular
systems
they give some more formalisms in 11
about blankets and couplings and flow
we'll go into it later
and 13 is very informative
the normal form means that particular
partitions can be defined in terms of
sparse couplings
perhaps the simplest definition
that guarantees a markov blanket is as
follows
external states only influence sensory
states
and
internal states only influence active
states
this means that sensory states are not
influenced by internal states
and
active states are not influenced by
external states
here's formalism 13. so recall
eta external s sensory a active mu
internal
so
f is the flow
and omega
is going to be the noise
and the subscript in
something is here like
tagging it
to be about that variable so
we have
the rates of change through time
here's like a vector or a tuple this
vector is describing the four states
and it's how external sense action and
internal states are changing
function of time
this
just like formula one
is going to be unpacked where we had x
dot of t
equals
flow plus noise
here we're doing like four of those in
parallel and so it's like
external states changing through time
is a flow on external states
as a function of
external sense and action
plus the noise of external states is a
function of time
so sense and external states
are a function of external sense and
action states
plus accompanied noise terms
whereas
action and internal states are functions
of
sense action and internal states
and so it's like external and sensory
states
are not being caused by internal states
that's the only missing guy here mew
it looks like nsa it's not it's eta sa
conversely the autonomous states
the ones that we have more agency over
the odd one out the missing you know
the dog that's not barking is etta
so these
autonomous states
are flows
on
sense action blankets
and internal states
so the bottom two rows are the
autonomous states
and those are defined as flows
of particular states
functions of flows that are using the
particular variables
whereas
the
external incense are driven by external
facing variables
how would you read that
under the sparse coupling it's simple to
show that path show that not only are
internal and external states
conditionally independent but their
paths are conditionally independent
given that path integral formulation
okay
any thoughts on
these last few
um
yeah again i just feel like
whether the math is landing for people
and this um
you know separation of the internal
states and the being
the the internal flows being conditioned
on
the sort of the atomic states right like
um
it's also it's just
partially like tautological or
just just makes
sense in the simple the way that the
model is presented
um
a couple slides back
i'm not sure if i guess this is the
right spot to bring it up though but um
thinking also about just so like
i think a question that i have
frequently about this is like
where did they come from where do things
come from well they come from you know
the separation and conditioning of you
know particularly from the background
and the blanket forming out of blankets
for him et cetera or where is
what's the difference between the
internal stay the extra like you said if
there's
you know this giant social graph doll
everything's connected they're all
connected then then there's no markup
blankets
um
just like two cells in the body how do
they know
that they're
not
um
[Music]
you know
they both have their own markov blankets
and yet they are both like external
states that are indistinguishable from
kind of the rest of stuff
to
themselves right
for each of them right
um
[Music]
like
over time
that
you know dissipates
right
and so
yeah i just i guess i wonder like
the overtime
um dot notation here like
how that
the dynamics of
how something becomes an
internal state or an external stage how
that exactly happens because again it
just seems like when you look at a lot
of examples
on you know our
entropic physics you know um anthropic
like um
state where we're right like everything
is good for us
um and everything we can observe right
because it's
like galaxies or something oh they're so
far away they don't you know there's a
lot of intergalactic
you know in space that's not affecting
it's very external
you rewind it a few billion years like
lots of interaction lots of
markov blankets so it's like um
yeah like
where does that
begin and end yeah
oh markov where art thy sting
yeah
um formalism 14 and 15
are
further details on the entropy of
internal and external paths and the
conditional independencies of paths
that's going to conclude section 4
particles partitions and things which
was about the markov blanket
partitioning
of particles particular states and so on
we'll move pretty quickly through the
following sections
section five from self-organization to
self-evidencing
equipped with a particular partition we
can
now talk about things in terms of their
internal states and markov boundary
namely autonomous states
and we can talk about particles
particular states
the next step is to characterize the
flow of the autonomous states
in relation to external states
in other words
considering the nature of the coupling
between the outside and inside of the
particle across its markov blanket
it is at this point that we move towards
a bayesian mechanics
that is the special provenance of
systems with particular partitions
the existence of a particular partition
means that given sensory states
one can define the conditional density
over external states as being
parameterized by the most likely
internal state and we had several
discussions in live stream 26 on
bayesian mechanics with lance decosta
this is where variational inference is
going to come into play we will call
this a variational density parameterized
by the internal mode
q
the distribution we control of
internal states
mu
about
external states eta is defined as
p
of external states conditioned on sense
equation 16 means that for every sensory
state there's a conditional density over
external states and a corresponding
internal mode with the smallest
surprisal
this mode specifies the variational
density
where by definition the kl divergence
between the variational density and the
conditional density over external states
is zero
more formalisms more details
inducing the variational density is an
important move
it means
that for every sensory state there is a
corresponding active mode and an
internal mode
this mode does not mean style here mode
means like the
most
common value in a statistical
distribution
the active and internal modes constitute
active and internal manifolds
we will see later that these manifolds
play the role of sensor manifolds namely
manifolds that contain paths that do not
diverge or converge exponentially
the open of exponents
the internal manifold is also a
statistical manifold because it is
equipped with a metric and implicit
information geometry
this is because movement on the internal
statistical manifold changes the
variational density
this is moving towards that dual
information
geometry perspective
what is equation 17 showing
we're looking at the flows
because if we're interested in those
paths of least action
we can discount that fluctuation term
the expectation of the fluctuations is
zero so we're able to drop those omegas
with a subscript that we saw in 13.
so now we're going to be looking at the
flows on
different states
as
for the top two the external and the
sense states those are going to be
about surprise
fracture i fancy i
for action
and internal states the autonomous
states
that is
free energy
minimizing surprise about external and
sensory states
minimizing free energy
about autonomous states
what is that f
the free energy in question is an upper
bound on the surprisal of particular
states
so in variational bayesian methods
elbow and free energy are used to bound
the surprisal
here we're bounding surprisal
on a particular partitioning
including action
to model the action perception loop
so
we've seen variational free energy
several times
what do these different rearrangements
mean
what other rearrangements or
restatements of f
are possible
they give a few
thoughts here
anything you want to add on variational
free energy
knowing that we'll have a lot of time to
go into that's why just bringing it up
that's what formalism 17 and 18 bring us
two
yeah
back to pat the path and a goal um you
know say like um
[Music]
it's
i'm wondering
my question is um in relation to action
and energy and the way this is being
stated like what
um
[Music]
yeah what is what is the
like action
version of this that's what is
like the
easy to miss like
oh it's just energy
um
thing that is
in the way of like framing this here um
because they're not the same thing
like so um
yeah that's my question is just
differentiating that or or
better defining
which parts are action which parts are
the energy components of that
that's what i would like be interested
in rearranging or thinking about yeah
these equations
cool
um they write in
footnote 19 is variational free energy
the same kind of free energy found in
thermodynamics
like
gibbs free energy perhaps
the answer is no
this entropy is distinct from the
thermodynamic entropy of internal states
we're going to return to this into half
are we talking about thermal free energy
or are we seeing equations that look
like descriptors of thermal entropy but
we're applying them in an informational
setting
we'll return to it
as they had brought up before
one can formulate
um
this along the lines of a center
manifold theorem
where we have a fast flow towards the
center manifold and a slow flow on the
manifold
going fast
towards the valley
ravine
and then
going slow on the river
this decomposition can be derived simply
using taylor expansion taylor series
expansion around the time varying
autonomous mode
so
here is a taylor series expansion
it's evaluating a function at a given
point
usually zero
and then
taking its first derivative
and then taking its second derivative
and using higher and higher derivatives
to approximate
increasing distances from the reference
single points where that
function was actually evaluated
so how is the taylor series expansion or
other
power series expansions
related to
time varying autonomous modes
what about that flow on the center
manifold we know from 17
that the flow of autonomous mode can be
expressed in terms of free energy
gradients
those are the two f's on the autonomous
um
so
this expression 20
unpacks the manifold flow in terms of
accuracy and complexity
parts of free energy where the accuracy
part depends on the sensory
states the complexity part is a function
of and only of
autonomous states
the manifold will look as if it is
trying to maximize the accuracy of its
predictions while complying with prior
bayesian beliefs
bayesian statistics these are all
bayesian variables
here predictions are read
as expected sensory states under
posterior bayesian beliefs about their
causes
namely variational density over external
states
the real temperature out there in the
room hidden unobserved external state
thermometer reading sensory state and
then states some sort of cognitive
mirror or representation
as modeled
of temperature
that's conditioned upon the thermometer
reading
but there's some generalized synchrony
across that
thermometer blanket
um in footnote 21.
they write question do particles
minimize surprisal or free energy
and we'll go into it because they say
minimization implies the teleology that
goes beyond any claim of the fep
whence
teleology
i thought we were like talking about
teleology earlier
so
how deep in the desert are we what what
what level of mirage are we engaging in
but we'll get there
and that takes us to
uh figure two
which is going to show two components of
autonomous flow conditioned upon sensory
states
so
i'll move us away
we can talk more about the technical
details like how it relies on the taylor
expansion
but here are the autonomous states
and the black line potentially can be
read as like that manifold attractor
and so there's a movement towards
directly towards
the attractor
and then
there's a movement
that is um
perhaps orthogonalized
keeping in mind the difference between
the gradient and the solenoidal flow
and together
through time so this is not just like a
hill
previously like in 26 we saw like the
hill and the particle makes its way to
the top of the hill as a function of
gradient ascent and solenoidal coupling
flow
here we're not just ascending a hill
like we're tracking this moving point
through time
but we're converging in this spiral way
and then we can maybe unpack that in
relationship to manifold flow
and how even if this black line is the
manifold
then
how is the entity staying on the
manifold
so
we'll talk more about figure two
now they're going to summarize this
section a particular partition of
non-equilibrium steady state nest
density implies autonomous dynamics can
be interpreted as performing inference
particular kind
it's not doing every kind it's doing a
specific kind and it's a particle
there's the fast flow towards the center
manifold and the slow flow on manifold
the manifold flow
can be interpreted as bayesian belief
updating and posterior bayesian beliefs
are encoded by points on the internal
states statistical manifold
in other words
for every point on the statistical
manifold that synchronization manifold
there's a corresponding variational
density or bayesian belief over external
states
these are internal states
about external states
conditioned on the particular
partitioning
and that can now be expressed as the
variational principle of leased action
this is the basis of the fep
put simply but not too simply i guess
it means that the internal states of a
particular partition can be cast as
encoding conditional or posterior
bayesian beliefs about external states
this license is a poetic description of
self-organization as self-evidencing
we'll unpack it later just wanted to
mention it so we can continue
in figure 3
several different ways
in which this self evidencing
is connected to various
theories
for example value surprise entropy and
model evidence
and the schematic is illustrating how
minimizing variational free energy
wait but i thought that minimization
implies the teleology that goes beyond
any claim of the fep
but minimizing variational free energy
relates to normative theories of optimal
behavior
like
value maximization
pragmatic reinforcement reward learning
pavlov
surprise
novelty info gain infomax
why is the free energy principle here
isn't it like
all of them
entropy
and model evidence as well
and then just to conclude the section
um
they ask is it tenable to interpret
gradient flows on variational free
energy landscapes
as variational inference or is this just
teleological window dressing
the next section addresses this question
through the lens of bayesian filtering
in brief we will see that autonomous
paths of least action implied by our
particular partition are the paths of
least action of a bayesian filter
this takes us beyond as if arguments
by establishing a formal connection
between particular dynamics and
variational inference
so
to discuss what are particular dynamics
what is variational inference
what is the relationship between
particular dynamics and variational
inference what would it mean for it to
be as if
and what would it mean for it to be
something different than as if
okay
continuing
on
six lagrangians generalized states and
bayesian filtering
now say we wanted to emulate or simulate
active inference
what if what if that were the case
we could find the stationary solution to
the faulker planck equation and the
accompanying helmholtz decomposition
we could then solve number 21
we call its paths of least action that
characterize the expected behavior of
this kind of particle
however there is a simpler way to
recover the paths of least action
by finding a path that minimizes
lagrangian at every point in time
noting from three that the path integral
of the lagrangian is the action
first they're going to reintroduce
generalized coordinates of motion
so we talked about that in number 26 as
well but the generalized coordinates of
motion are like the position
velocity acceleration and higher and
higher and higher derivatives
of
the coordinates of location
so it's taking like the x y coordinates
and adding their first derivative and
their second derivative and their third
derivative and just having that in a
vector so that's what's shown here
x through time
the derivative of x x prime
is a flow
the second derivative
the first derivative and so on that's
the integrator chains pid control and so
on
in the generalized coordinates of motion
state velocity acceleration and so on
are treated as separate generalized
states that are coupled through the
jacobian
so if the first and the second are
related to each other in the second and
third and third and the fourth there's a
sparse coupling in that
vector
this allows us to relax certain
assumptions
and gives a quadratic form
we'll unpack this more but
there's a sparsity
and a capacity to do
modeling of movement in the generalized
coordinates of motion now maybe three
maybe six are sufficient but this is
like an infinite dimensional framework
but it may be the case that you can go
super far with like just
a few
um
formalisms 23 and 24
describe
that m can be read as a mass matrix
that would be interesting to know what
is meant there and there's a suggestion
that precise particles
with low amplitude random fluctuations
behave like massive bodies
so that's like the baseball on the the
parabola the air fluctuations and the
thermal vibrations are not dominating
its trajectory but the one molecule
baseball it is getting tossed and turned
in equation 25 and 26
they continue describing
using that helmholtz
decomposition the divergence free flow
and the curl free flow
in terms of the gradient descent
on a lagrangian
that'll be helpful to learn what they
mean
and then crucially when that is
minimized
the mode of the path becomes the path of
the mode
that would be something useful to
understand what is meant
what's the difference between tracking
the mean
and tracking the mode
for gaussian distributions
like the laplace approximation or any
other second order
curvature
what does that
mean
and then just to close this section
the generalized free energy is easy to
evaluate
thankfully
given a generative model in the form of
a state-space model
here it is
f
of sense action and internal
is going to be
some terms
that we'll learn about
and finally one can simulate active
inference
by replacing the generalized flow of
autonomous states with a generalized
bayesian filter
so here we have 27.
very similar
except notice that there's a lot more
arrows
and
the bottom two
instead of 13
we now have these bottom two rows with
the d on a
and the d on mu
and some triangles have been introduced
we'll unpack more what that
means any thoughts or comments or we'll
continue to seven
so yeah
awesome
sevens from statistical to classical
particles
so far we have a bayesian mechanics that
would be apt to describe a particle or
person with pullback attractor but what
is the difference between a particle and
a person
this speaks
to distinct classes of things to which
fep could apply molecular versus
biological versus
here we associate biotic
self-organization with precise and
predictable dynamics of large particles
so as we described earlier
if we were talking about classical
mechanics something bigger would be more
resistant to like thermal fluctuation
we could think about like that analogy
to mass in the statistical setting
where are the priors like massive and
they're just on their own inertia and
they're not being buffeted by
stochasticity versus where is it a
lightweight
something
that is getting buffeted
so here's going to be a distinction
between statistical and classical
mechanics in the setting of the
particular partition
it is often said
that the fep explains why biological
systems resist the second law
tendency towards disorder
and the natural tendency to dissipation
and disorder
however
this is disingenuous on two counts
so is first in 2013 disingenuous
or is that paper
combating
the disingenuity
first the second law applies only to
closed systems while the free energy
principle describes open systems
in which internal states are exposed to
and exchange with external states
through blanket
states with lots of unpacked there what
exactly is the exchange
is it like an informational exchange
or are like nutrients crossing and
becoming incorporated into the internal
states
and second there is nothing so far to
suggest that the entropy of particular
states or of paths is small
so this is like the design language for
particular states that might be totally
buffeted by stochasticity or totally on
the least action railroad and everything
in between
but nothing has been said to identify
um one or the other
and so everything's high and low entropy
densities
so there's you know two particles in two
different rooms one particle is equally
traveling to all parts of the room the
other particle is staying in one part of
the room
so
one of them has a very ordered
distribution of space and the other one
has a very like disordered you know
equilibrium gas flowing throughout the
room
both of them are particles
um so what distinguishes between
high and low entropy systems
eg between candle flames and concierges
respectively
we could have had a concierge
and that is going to
describe that and we'll come back to it
this suggests that precise particles
such as you and me
respond to environmental flows and
fluctuations in a precise and
predictable fashion well i'm an
unpredictable guy
yes
in
our regime of attention
it is almost like tuned to some
maximally confusing or uninformative
things or we could have some cognitive
experience of being confused but um
someone's blood sugar through time has
more predictability than zero so it's on
that continuum from totally buffeted to
totally on the railroad tracks and it's
more like the railroad tracks if you
want to survive
or design high reliability systems
and then they're going to introduce
figures four five and six
four is about the difference between
generic and precise particles using an
information diagram
for precise particles there's no
uncertainty about autonomous states
given sensory states
knowledge about action knowledge about
internal states like metacognition
um is the behavior of precise particles
sufficient for sentient behavior
perhaps
figure five the implicit computational
architecture used in simulations of
sentient behavior
and six is reproducing an example from
the octave literature with action and
action observation
so
figure four
has to do with information gain and
sharing with generic and precise
particles
do you wanna add anything otherwise
we'll just take one look at each of four
five and six
okay
figure five bayesian mechanics
graphic summarizes belief updating
implicit in gradient flows on
variational free energy
and six
sentient behavior and action observation
so this is like
somebody involved in pointing or tracing
or handwriting
and also
looking visually
in summary
precise particles
immersed in an imprecise world respond
almost deterministically to external
fluctuations
why might this behavior be
characteristically biological
precise particles may be the kind of
particles that show lifelike or biotic
behavior so let's think of those two
particles in the two rooms one of them
24 hours a day no matter what the
temperature is or what the light dark
cycle is it's always equally covering
all parts of the room
the other particle
you find out that when it's light it
stays in this part of the room
and then when it's dark it stays in this
other part of the room
which one of those particles without
knowing anything more seems more
biological the one that's diffusing like
a gas molecule or the one that has this
orderly distribution
especially one that's conditioned upon
like salient external factors
so
the distinction between those imprecise
and precise particles
getting buffeted
by thermal vibrations
or
being like the classical like the kepler
universe like the planets going around
orbits
totally unbuffeted by thermal vibrations
rests on their relative contribution of
dissipative and conservative flow to
their path through state space one might
associate precise particles with living
systems with characteristic biorhythms
and then they bring up
many many nested biorhythms
from
rapid oscillations that are multiple
times per second
in neural systems
heartbeat respiratory circadian
seasonal
life cycles even pulling out to the
evolutionary angle
turning this on its head one can argue
living systems are a certain kind of
particle
the in virtue of being precise events
conservative dynamics
biorhythms and time irreversibility so
wow how are these all related to each
other where does the time
irreversibility connect
and
their summary
the emerging picture is that biotic
systems
feature solenoidal flow
in virtue of being sufficiently large to
average away random fluctuations when
coarse graining their dynamics
and figure 6 explores that more
okay final
technical section 8
path integrals planning and curious
particles
the previous section was focused on
linking dynamics
changes through time
to densities over generalized states
internal states can be construed as
parameterizing bayesian beliefs about
external states
internal states are about external
states in this model
in what follows we move from densities
over states to densities over paths to
characterize the behavior of particles
in terms of their trajectories
so
formalism 29
we're interested in characterizing
autonomous responses to initial
particular states autonomous
the action and internal states the ones
that we control
recall that when random fluctuations on
the motion of particular states vanish
there's no uncertainty about autonomous
paths given external and sensory paths
knowing exactly what to do and exactly
what to think
and there's no uncertainty about sensory
paths given external and autonomous
paths
knowing exactly what senses will be
observed
given the external world and the
autonomous paths which is what one does
and thinks
if we interpret entropies as the
limiting density of discrete points
figure four
then the uncertainty
about particular
autonomous
and sensory paths given external paths
become interchangeable
formalism 30 formalism 31 expected free
energy
the autonomous path with the least
expected free energy
is the most likely path taken by the
autonomous states
expected free energy
how can we read it what does it mean
why does it matter that we're focusing
on autonomous states
autonomous paths
and how is it similar or different from
other representations that we've seen
and that we will see affected free
energy and free energy of the expected
future and so on
expected free energy prints
where it can be regarded as a fairly
universal objective function
for selecting paths of least action
planning planning as bayesian inference
equation 33
expected free energy
expected action
bayesian optimal decisions
utility pragmatic value
expectations of information gain
optimal info gain bayes optimal
experimental design optimal
hypothesizing
so not just falsification not to beat a
dead horse
but
rather than constraining
and then executing
keeping this infinite game optimal
design perspective open
so that we can always be tier
of the balance between optimal decision
making and optimal experimenting
when simulating with active inference
and planning afforded by path integral
formulation one usually works with
discrete state spaces and belief
updating over discrete epochs of time
that's where the partially observable
markov decision process pomdp comes into
play
and plausible policies can then be
scored
evaluated based upon their expected free
energy
and the next action is selected from the
most likely policy policies or sequences
of actions that can be taken
in summary we now have at hand a way of
identifying the most likely autonomous
trajectory from any initial particular
state
that can be used to simulate sentient
behavior of precise particles that we
have associated with biotic systems
expected free energy absorbs two aspects
of bayes optimality into the same
objective functional
which is a function with functions
the information gain
is optimal bayesian design
bayesian decision theory is minimizing a
cost function under a decision or choice
and uncertainty
as with the interpretation of
variational free energy
this dual aspect functionality of
expected free energy is an
interpretation of a single existential
imperative
to possess a markov blanket and implicit
thickness
teleologically it's worth reflecting
upon the differences between the
generative models that underwrite
variational and expected free energy
for vfe
the generative model is a joint density
over external and particular states
supplied by or supplying the
non-equilibrium steady state density
for the path integral formulation
the generative model is a joint
distribution over paths
because consequences
the generative model acquires a temporal
depth
they then have several figures that
continue on this theme
figure seven
is um related to a
decosta 2020 discrete state space
synthesis paper
showing special cases of variational and
expected free energy
like when there's no preference
there's optimal information gain
when there's no ambiguity you get pure
risk sensitive policy
when there's no intrinsic value you get
expected utility theory and when there's
no ambiguity or preferences some recent
work by ramstead
at all have
started to
soft reboot the fep and connect
connecticut principle which we're going
to be looking forward to learning more
about
figure eight is a about bayesian
mechanics and active inference so we can
contrast that with figure five bayesian
mechanics and active inference
figure eight bayesian mechanics and
active inference
figure 9 is a simulation in which eye
cicades are occurring
and we can explore this more
to the conclusion
there are many points of contact between
what we described and other theories
please
read the papes
discuss special cases
they discuss the mechanics of
synchronization
separation of time scale and
applications
and then
in closing
they write about how
the developments
are speaking to the shift in focus from
the foundational issues addressed in
this article to their applications
learning and applying active inference
and fep
it is quite possible that the
foundational aspects of the free energy
principle may also shift as simpler
interpretations and perspectives reveal
themselves
that brings us to the end of the dot
zero so
brock
what would you like to add or say
i would like to add that for the next
stop zero i will be preparing my answer
to this part first um ahead of time
um
i don't know just writing down a few
things and thinking about um
[Music]
intractability and
uncertainty and
um
possible kind of informational
information entropy kind of um questions
that you could ask around that like what
what makes those kind of ultimate markov
blankets of intractability um
like how action intensive is it
for information to cross like
or or for
external for the external um states to
influence the
indirectly influence the internal states
right
and another question
how hard do you have to push on the
blanket what kind of push and what so
yes they're conditionally independent
but also they do influence each other
the blanket so how hard you have to push
yeah
um
and it just it seems like i guess what
i'm saying is that um
the scale
uh which we kind of
you're using the particle people
and the baseball
um analogy right um
and we talked about that
yesterday or the day about um like
um
just a large you know matrix large space
of
states of variables of you know
um dimensions of of what you mean by a
markov blanket in a particular you know
and the scale of that markov blanket to
the environment right
um
having like a big
seeming
to have a like a big impact on
how hard you have to push there
right
um the baseball's flying through the air
but the
particle is
spreading out and you know being pushed
around and yeah and i was like are we
little molecules
trying to push the baseball
or are we
the designated hitter
who's way overpowered and able to put it
wherever we want or are we just doing
the tiniest buffeting
maybe this is a design language that
helps us frame both of those settings
and recognize when are we able to
be
guiding the path of least action
and where might no matter how hard we
yell
maybe we're not influencing it like
literally at all
or
stick out we're influencing it like
stick out like stochastically it's not
we can't kind of concentrate our action
into one
you know
path right um one pet like so
yeah there's i don't know there's a lot
of um
wonderings and questions that are like
not
uh
probably very well informed to just
read the papes
on and continue reducing uncertainty
um
yeah
awesome work with this dot zero and
thanks a ton for being a part of it
thanks to everybody for watching and all
the great comments in the chat
and we'll see you
in the dot one and the dot two
bye awesome
thank you
you